Finding Aid for Todd Family Papers, 1862-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Todd Family Papers 1862-1980, 1889-1980
Todd family.
1 oversize volume
3.4 linear feet
85567 Aa 2; AC
Family of Fred P. Todd and his son, J. Beecher Todd, officers with National Loan and Investment Company in Detroit, Michigan, and its successor institutions, Surety Savings and Loan Association, and Surety Federal Savings and Loan Association. The collection consists of personal papers, files relating to their activities with savings and loan institutions, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mr. and Mrs. J. Beecher Todd (donor no. 7023 ) in January 1984.
The collection is open to research.
In 1889, the National Loan and Investment Company was formed in Detroit and was one of the city's first Building and Loan companies. After forty fairly prosperous years, the company was forced to liquidate its assets in the early 1930s because of a significant embezzlement loss and the adverse affects of the depression. In its place, Surety Savings and Loan was established in 1938 with the same officers as had previously been with National Loan and Investment. Surety Savings became Surety Federal Savings and Loan in 1959 after a new Federal charter had been acquired.
Fred P. Todd, Sr. served in various capacities with all three organizations, ranging from his first job as clerk with National Loan in 1899 to his last position as Chairman of the Board of Surety Federal, from which he resigned in 1960. His son, J. Beecher Todd, served with both Surety Savings and Surety Federal, and like his father, held a variety of positions, including branch manager and vice-president.
Surety Federal Savings and Loan Association no longer exists. In 1981, it was merged into First Federal Savings and Loan of Oakland County.
The Todd Family Papers consist of three series: Personal, Savings and Loan Institutions, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Banks and banking--Michigan--Detroit.; Berrien County (Mich.); Business records.; Detroit (Mich.)--Commerce.; National Loan and Investment Company.; Surety Federal Savings and Loan Association.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 25th (1862-1865). Company C.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Banking.; Banks.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Detroit.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Eastpointe.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Plymouth.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Redford.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Rochester.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Southfield.; Interiors--Banks.; Mackinac Island (Mich.); National Loan and Investment Company.; Sunday, Billy, 1862-1935.; Surety Federal Savings and Loan Association.; Todd, Fred P.; Todd, J. Beecher.
Contributors:
Carlisle, Joseph L.; Todd, Fred P.; Todd, J. Beecher.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Tintypes.
- Personal
  The Personal series is small and contains Todd Family correspondence and scrapbook materials. Of particular interest to the researcher should be the perceptive and observant Civil War letters written by Joseph L. Carlisle, of the Michigan 25th Infantry. Mr. Carlisle was a cousin of Fred P. Todd's wife, Mary Costello Todd.
  - Civil War letters 1862-1865 (Box 1)
    (mostly written by Joseph L. Carlisle, Michigan 25th Infantry)
  - Miscellaneous letters written in 1908 to George Normahls, family relative, recuperating from tuberculosis in New Mexico (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook (mostly clippings), 1895-1935 (Box 1)
- Savings and Loan Institutions
  The Savings and Loan Institutions series is primarily devoted to the three institutions in which Fred P. Todd, Sr. and his son, J. Beecher Todd, worked and served as officers. Major sequences within the series are: General; National Loan and Investment Company; Surety Savings and Loan Association; and Surety Federal Savings and Loan Association. Each sequence is organized topically. Minutes from Board of Directors meetings; annual reports; organizational material; and scrapbooks are helpful in tracing the activities and history of each institution. News and Good Living, quarterly publications of Surety Savings and Surety Federal Savings, are brief in scope and general in content, but do contain semi-annual financial statements, promotional advertisements, and occasional employee-related information.
  - General
    - Todd, Fred P., Sr.
      - Biographical (Box 1)
      - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Todd, J. Beecher
      - Biographical (Box 1)
      - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Organization History (Box 1)
      (very brief history of National Loan and Investment Company, Surety Savings and Loan Association, and Surety Federal Savings and Loan Association)
  - National Loan and Investment Company
    - Asset Statements 1890-1944 (Box 1)
    - Board of Directors Meetings
      - 1918-1924 (Box 1)
      - March 1, 1930 (Box 1)
      - 1934-1940 (Volume 1)
    - Final Liquidation (Box 1)
    - Organizational Materials (Box 1)
    - President's Annual Report to Shareholders 1935-1938, 1940-1944 (Box 1)
  - Surety Savings and Loan Association
    - Abstract of Title (Box 1)
    - Board of Directors and Executive Officers
      - General (Box 1)
      - Meetings 1948-1953, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Branches (Redford) (Box 2)
    - Clippings (Box 2)
    - Consumer credit: Regulation "W" (Box 2)
    - Court papers (Miscellaneous) (Box 2)
    - Employees (Box 2)
    - Federal Home Loan Bank: Application for membership (Box 2)
    - Michigan State Board of Escheats (Box 2)
    - Organizational materials (includes financial statements) (Box 2)
    - President's annual report to shareholders 1939-1957 (Box 2)
    - Real estate credit: Regulation "X" (Box 2)
    - Semiannual reports 1938-1953 (Box 2)
      (Miscellaneous: Earnings/dividends; Closed loans; Comparisons)
    - Shareholders meetings 1941-1948, 1952, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Surety Federal Savings and Loan Association
    - Board of directors and executive officers (Box 2)
      (includes clippings on director Stanley S. Kresge)
    - Branches
      - Avon (clippings) (Box 2)
      - Eastland (includes photos) (Box 2)
      - Plymouth (Box 2)
    - Bylaws (Box 2)
    - Charter N (Box 2)
    - Clippings 1957-1966 (Box 2)
    - Employees (Box 2)
    - Home office relocation circa 1976 (Box 2)
    - Organizational materials (Box 2)
      (includes some financial statements)
  - Publications and scrapbooks
    - Surety Savings and Surety Federal publications: News and Good Living (Box 3)
    - National Loan and Investment Company 1891-1944 (Box 3)
      (includes photos of Campus Martius and Griswold Street, Detroit, ca. 1890 and interior of bank, 1930s ?)
    - Surety Savings and Loan Association 1938-1961 (Box 3)
      (includes photos of exterior of Griswold Street bank, 1930s ? and 1950s ?, exterior and interior of Redford branch, billboards)
    - Surety Federal Savings and Loan Association 1962-1979 (Box 3)
      (includes photos of exterior, interior, and staff of Eastland branch, construction, exterior, and interior of Plymouth branch, construction and exterior of Avon branch)
- Photographs
  Among the Photographs are views of the National Loan and Investment Company office in Detroit, Surety Federal Savings offices in Detroit, East Detroit, Plymouth, Redford, Avon, and Southfield, Michigan, and photos of Todd family activities including vacations at Mackinac Island, Michigan. Of special mention are photos of Billy Sunday in Detroit in 1916 and a tintype of trumpeters in military uniforms.
  - Family (Box 4)
    (loose snapshots from album)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - National Loan and Investment Company (Box 4)
  - Surety Federal Savings and Loan Association
    - Eastland branch, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Main office 1250 Griswold (Box 4)
    - Main office, Southfield, opening (Box 4)
    - Plymouth branch (Box 4)
    - Plymouth branch album 1971 (Box 4)
  - Family album 1911-1918 (Box 4)
    (includes photos of Billy Sunday in Detroit, 1916)
  - Tintype of two trumpet players in uniform, circa 1870 (Box 4)